Preliminary Guide to the Naval Science Department records, 1944-1991 RG0042
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Naval Science Department records
1944-1991
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Naval Science
RG0042
1 Linear Feet 2 half hollingers 1 full hollinger
Materials in this collection include yearbooks, brochures, research reports, and an audio cassette. They range in date from 1950-1991.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Naval Studies Department.
Historical Note
In 1983 the Board of Trustees of The George Washington University approved plans to establish a Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps (NROTC). As part of the agreement between the University and the Navy, GW established training courses, which combined with University courses, comprise a program in naval science. Especially pertinent to naval science instruction are courses in GW's School of Engineering and Applied Science.
NROTC midshipmen are required to complete the naval science courses and attend weekly professional seminars. During the summer, NROTC midshipmen participate in active duty at sea or shore-based training cruises for approximately four weeks. Upon receiving the baccalaureate and completing the NROTC program, qualified midshipmen are commissioned as ensigns in the Naval Reserve or second lieutenants in the Marine Corps Reserve. Commissioned naval officers go on to training in various warfare specialties and serve as surface or submarine officers, naval aviators, or SEALs. Marine Corps officers attend basic school in Quantico, Virginia, and serve in fields such as infantry, artillery, and aviation. Staff positions (intelligence, law, medicine) are not normally offered through NROTC.
Enrollment in NROTC is not a requirement for taking naval science courses. Any student enrolled at George Washington University may take naval science courses with the approval of the Professor of Naval Science. GW also offered courses in Military Science and Tactics from 1928-53.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include yearbooks, brochures, research reports, and an audio cassette. They range in date from 1950-91, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Naval Studies Department.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Naval ROTC, Departmental files, Reprints.
Audiocassettes
- Navy ROTC, 1950-1991; RG0042 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of GW Naval ROTC yearbooks and brochures, and an audio cassette of the 1987 commencement. The materials range in date from 1950-91.
  Formerly ACC#68
  - NROTC proposal and documents for GW, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State of the unit report, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GW NROTC yearbook, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - GW NROTC yearbook "Amidships", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - GW NROTC yearbook "Amidships", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GW NROTC program brochures, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Audio cassette of 1987 commencement (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Departmental files, 1944-1962; RG0042 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of class research reports, war training courses room schedule, and a WWII lab notebook. The materials range in date from 1944-62.
  Formerly ACC#556
  - The Dollar Problem - Matching the Mission with Money, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Rocket Ordnance: Development and Use in World War II, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Control of Funds - The Anti-Deficiency Story, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - WWII Military oriented Research lab notebook, 1944 -- --ca. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Engineering, Science, and Management War Training Courses Room Schedule, 09/05/1944 -- ---12/15/1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reprints, 1947-1978; RG0042 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of two volumes of reprints by A.M. Sullivan for the naval research laboratory. The materials range in date from 1947-78.
  Formerly ACC#661
  This series is unprocessed, please ask staff for assistance.